Good morning. Today's דף daf is מ"ח. mem-ches. And we picked up
at the almost towards the bottom of מ"ז עמוד ב' mem-zayin amud-beis
at the two dots. If you had remembered, we had discussed the
issue about the status by קמיצה, kemitzah, not by חפינה, chafina, but
by קמיצה, kemitzah, the normal קמיצה kemitzah of a מנחה, mincha, about
the stuff that's between the fingers, whether it's considered part of the
קמיצה kemitzah or not, or whether as the תוספות Tosafot understood the
answer to be that like objectively it's a ספק, safek, and then
how do you handle it in order to burn it appropriately? So
now the גמרא Gemara continues after the two dots with the words
in parenthesis, בעי רב פפא: ba'i Rav Papa: So רב פפא Rav
Papa asked, now that we've had this discussion by the קמיצה, kemitzah,
ביני ביני דמלא חפניו מהו? beini beini d'mlo chofnov mahu? How about
the קטורת ketoret that gets stuck between the fingers by the double
scoops of the hands for the קטורת? ketoret?
So let's take a look.
Yeah, it's true. The way you scoop it up, it's harder to
imagine that that would happen, but it's an interesting theoretical question. מאי
קמיבעיא ליה? mai kamibaia lei? What's exactly the nature of the question
says the גמרא? Gemara? אי גמר מלא מלא מהתם, i gmar mlo
mlo mehatam, if you learn out מלא חפניו mlo chofnov from מלא
קומצו, mlo kumtzo, right? That's, if you learn the חפינה chafina from
the קמיצה, kemitzah, so the גמרא Gemara says היינו הך, hainu hach,
that's exactly the question we raised before because if you remember, the
גמרא Gemara earlier had the question whether can you take just the
measure of the scoops of the hand or do you actually have
to do the scooping? By the קמיצה, kemitzah, we know you have
to do this taking of the hand-breath with your hand itself. The
question is by the חפינה, chafina, could it just be מלא חפניו?
mlo chofnov? And the גמרא's Gemara question was, do you learn out
חפינה chafina from קמיצה? kemitzah? Do you learn out מלא מלא? mlo
mlo? So if that's the question here, whether you learn out חפינה
chafina from קמיצה, kemitzah, it's the same question. So whatever the answer
is there, the answer will be here. So is that the issue?
So the גמרא Gemara says no, רב פפא הכי בעי. Rav Papa
hachi ba'i. No, here he assumes he has a special question.
What's the question here? הכי קמיבעיא ליה: hachi kamibaia lei: מלא חפניו
והביא בעינן ואיכא? mlo chofnov v’hevi beinun v’ika? The פסוק pasuk says
ולקח הכהן גחלי אש מעל המזבח, v’lakach hakohen gachalei esh me’al hamizbeach,
what the פסוק pasuk is, קח לך אש מעל המזבח ומלא חפניו
קטורת סמים דקה והביא מבית לפרוכת. kach lecha esh me’al hamizbeach u’mlo
chofnov ketoret samim daka v’hevi mibeit laparochet. So the question is, where
does that verb ולקח v’lakach go on, right? It's ולקח הכהן גחלי
אש מעל המזבח,
v’lakach hakohen gachalei esh
me’al hamizbeach, that's what we discussed last time, which מזבח mizbeach it
was, when are they considered גחלי אש
מעל המזבח?
gachalei esh me’al
hamizbeach? Anyway, ומלא חפניו קטורת סמים דקה והביא.
u’mlo chofnov
ketoret samim daka v’hevi. So והביא v’hevi is going on both
of these, right? And that's how we learned that you have to
do it all in one act. It's one הבאה hava’ah for both
of them. The question the גמרא Gemara is asking is now, how
about the verb ולקח? v’lakach?
Is it ולקח גחלי אש v’lakach gachalei esh and ומלא חפניו u’mlo
chofnov and you'll bring them in? Or is it ולקח גחלי אש
ולקח מלא חפניו? v’lakach gachalei esh v’lakach mlo chofnov?
What's the difference? You could have said what, well, yeah, the question
is, is it explicit? And the גמרא's Gemara going to assume that
that difference determines this issue of the stuff between the fingers. Because
it imagines that when you're scooping it up, okay, if stuff gets
between the fingers, that's inadvertent. That doesn't come in the natural act,
like as Michael was saying, like maybe when you're scooping, maybe it's
more naturally the act is putting stuff in between your fingers.
But here when you're scooping, the act of לקיחה lekichah is only
the stuff in the palms of your hand. And if something gets
in, it hasn't had an act of לקיחה lekichah done to it.
It just happened to have inadvertently gotten there. That's the way the
גמרא Gemara understands the reality. So let's just read it. So that's
what the גמרא Gemara says the question is here. Do you בעינן?
beinun? הכי בעינן: hachi beinun: מלא חפניו והביא בעינן? mlo chofnov v’hevi
beinun? The only verb you focus on מלא חפניו mlo chofnov is
the bringing it in, not the act of taking. ואיכא. v’ika. So
fine, so you've brought it in and it happens to be in
your hands. That's fine.
Then right,
then that's included because that was what was, it's considered conceptually part
of the fill of your hands, so it's okay to be brought
in. I mean, that you have to say is the assumption. Maybe
it's not even considered מלא חפניו, mlo chofnov, but okay. או דלמא,
o dilma, or do you say ולקח והביא בעינן? v’lakach v’hevi beinun?
You need the act of taking it and the stuff that got
between your fingers wasn't taken and therefore it's not included. והא ליכא,
v’ha lika, and you don't have it. So the גמרא Gemara says
תיקו. teiku. Of course, it is funny that the גמרא Gemara assumes
that it's within the category of מלא חפניו. mlo chofnov. You could
have said that's external to מלא חפניו. mlo chofnov. Yes.
Okay.
So, so that's the question there about the stuff between the fingers.
אמר רב פפא: Amar Rav Papa: Now we're getting to the act
of doing the קמיצה kemitzah and the act of doing the חפינה.
chafina. פשיטא לי, pishita li, it's obvious to me, מלא קומצו, mlo
kumtzo, when the תורה Torah says the fill of
his hand. it would be a normal way a person would do
a קמיצה. kemitzah. What would be a normal way a person would
do a קמיצה? kemitzah? So Charlie is doing like this, right? The
רש"י Rashi says no, the assumption is you do like this, you
put your hand in and you scoop it out like that. Okay,
so now that's obvious that that's what it means to me. But
how about variations on that? Is that included in מלא קומצו? melo
kumtzo? Does it really matter how you do the act of קמיצה?
kemitzah? Okay, so בעי
רב פפא, baei Rav Pappa, so רב פפא Rav Pappa asks, קמץ
בראשי אצבעותיו מהו. kematz b'rashei etzbaotav mahu. Let's say you use the
tips of your fingers, meaning basically your palm was down and you
scooped it up into your palm like that.
Like you clear the table of crumbs on
שבת.
Shabbos. That's how you do it? I do it like this.
Okay, anyway,
okay. מלמטה למעלה מהו? milmata l'mala mahu? From below to above, what's...
so רש"י Rashi says basically means the back of your hand is
down and you scoop up like that. Which some might say that's
כדקמצי אינשי, kidekamzi inshi, that's the shovel way is the easiest way.
מהו. mahu.
מן הצדדים מהו? min hatzedadim mahu? From the sides. Now what's the
sides? This sounds like the sides. But רש"י Rashi says no, the
sides means you put your hand down like this and rather than...
you don't scoop it in at an angle, you put it flat
and you like try to scoop it in like, you know, you're
sort of like at a slight angle, you know, with your stuff
into it. But it's not like you're going down like scooping it
like that. You're sort of getting it to come off from the
sides of your hand onto your palm. What's the story? And with
all of those, the גמרא Gemara says תיקו, teiku, we don't know.
Now, of course you could say the question is that the גמרא
Gemara assumes you need to do it naturally. Of course it's fascinating
what's natural, right? And the question is what's included in the range
of the normal, like how much, what's the range of the normal.
Or you could say maybe the question is, and this gets to
the issue before,
more by the חפינה chafinah than the קמיצה, kemitzah, of how significant
is the act of taking. Remember the גמרא Gemara had the question
by the חפינה chafinah maybe you don't need an act of חפינה,
chafinah, you just need that measure. By the קמיצה kemitzah you need
the act of the קמיצה. kemitzah. But maybe even if you need
the act of the קמיצה, kemitzah, how much do we sort of
ritualize the act and have requirements by the act, or do we
just sort of say, you know, no, as however you do it,
it doesn't matter, just do some type of thing that gets it
all into your hand? So it could be that that's the question,
but it doesn't sound like that. It sounds like it's clear from
the גמרא Gemara you need a type of a formally defined act,
and the question is what falls within that range. Okay, so it
doesn't know exactly the answer. אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Pappa, and
now we're going to move on from קמיצה, kemitzah, of course, to
חפינה. chafinah.
פשיטא לי, Pshita li, it's obvious to me, מלא חפניו melo chofnav
כדחפני אינשי, kidechafni inshi, it would be the normal way people would
scoop up with both their hands. בעי, Baei, which I guess... which
probably is similar, probably is you come in with the edge of
your hands at an angle, this is the way רש"י Rashi says,
you know, you scoop it up together. However, בעי רב פפא, baei
Rav Pappa, same type of question. חפן בראשי אצבעותיו מהו? chafan b'rashei
etzbaotav mahu? Let's say again you sort of use... your palm's down
and you scooped it, you know, with the tips of your fingers
into your palms. מלמטה למעלה מהו? milmata l'mala mahu? Again, the backs
of your hands are down and you do it down at an
angle like that. Okay,
מן הצד מהו? min hatzad mahu? Again, like we said before, your
hands are sort of flat and you're getting it to come over
the edge of your hands. Now we have another question because now
we're dealing with two hands. חפן בזו ובזו chafan b'zo u'v'zo if
you did a חפינה chafinah with each hand separately, וקירבן זו אצל
זו. v'kervan zu etzel zu. After you had each one hand breadth,
you brought the two together. Rather than like a scooping that brings
it all together with the two coming together at once. So and
the answer to all of that is תיקו. teiku. Now I should
say, by the way, that here it's funny that it has an
identical question because we had a question before whether you needed an
act of חפינה chafinah altogether. Remember before we had the possibility that
maybe it's just מלא חפניו, melo chofnav, maybe you don't need an
act of חפינה. chafinah. So this question certainly seems to take for
granted that you need an act of חפינה, chafinah, and therefore is
asking how similar is it to the question, or parallel questions to
that of the act of קמיצה. kemitzah. Okay, now בעי רב פפא,
baei Rav Pappa, רב פפא Rav Pappa had another question.
דהקי לקומץ בדופני דמנא מאי? dahakei l'kometz b'dofnei damana mai? So the
act of קמיצה kemitzah we learn elsewhere, if you take the קמיצה
kemitzah and then you put the קמיצה kemitzah from the מנחה minchah
that you have in your hand into a כלי שרת. kli sharet.
And that act of putting it in a כלי שרת kli sharet
is part of the act of bringing the קמיצה, kemitzah, it's part
of what sanctifies the קמיצה kemitzah now to be brought to the
altar because think about it, this is going to be relevant for
what we're going to say in a minute, there are parallels of
the קמיצה kemitzah to the מנחה minchah to the שחיטה shechitah of
an animal. You do the קמיצה kemitzah which is an act of
separating and it separates the part that's going to go on the
altar from the part that stays behind. And that's parallel to the
שחיטה shechitah which basically releases the blood that's going to go on
the altar and releases and is an act of cutting and leaves
behind what'll be behind. Then what do you do with the blood?
You catch the blood in a vessel. So what do you do
with the קמיצה? kemitzah? You have to take the קמיצה kemitzah and
put that in a vessel. Then you throw the blood on the
altar or you first you transport it to the altar, you transport
the... to the altar, you throw the blood on the altar, and
you put the קמיצה kmitza on the fire. So one of those
steps of the four steps of putting the קמיצה kmitza into the
vessel. And now we're going to ask what constitutes an act of
putting it into the vessel. So let's take a look at what
the question is.
קמיצה kmitza is an action, right? Right, קומץ. kometz.
I meant the קומץ, kometz, excuse me. All right, thank you. You
put the קומץ, kometz, thank you, sorry. You do the קמיצה, kmitza,
then you put the קומץ kometz into the vessel, bring it to
the altar and put it on the altar. Okay, so בעי רב
פפא. Ba'ei Rav Pappa. דבקה לקומץ, Dveka lakometz, thank you, there it
is right in the גמרא. Gemara. You stuck the קומץ kometz בדופני
דמנא bedofnei demana against the wall of the vessel. You didn't put
it on the floor, you didn't let it drop to hit the
floor of the vessel. You stuck it against the wall. מאי? Mai?
What's the הלכה? halacha? Does that count? The same way there's a
קבלת דם kabbalas dam in a vessel, there has to be a
קבלה kabbala of the קומץ kometz in the vessel and a sanctifying
of the קומץ kometz in the vessel. Does this count? תוכה בעינן
ואיכא? Tocho ba'inan ve'ika? All you need is for it to get
into the interior of the vessel and it's in the interior of
the vessel. או דילמא הנחה בתוכו כתיקנו בעינן והכא ליכא? O dilma
hanacha betocho ketikno ba'inan vehacha leika? You need it to be placed
in it like normally. Again, like the idea we said before about
the act of קמיצה. kmitza. To what degree does it have to
be normal, the normal way it's done? Maybe you need it to
hit the floor of the vessel as is normal and you don't
have that.
Normal way, in other words, I thought you know whole point was
that by קדשים kodashim unless you have an הלכה halacha then you
do whichever in any which way you want and very few things
are מעכב. me'akev.
Yeah, so I don't know, I mean again I suppose because it's
more tangible, like I guess in theory you could have asked the
question by the blood, let's say you angled the vessel
so you know so the floor of the vessel was pointing up
and somehow it was an uneven you know wall anyway that the
blood got in. Maybe if it or what happens if the blood
got in and was sort of suspended, you know held by the
wall of the vessel without actually hitting the floor. So supposedly you
could have asked a serious a similar question, but it's easier when
you're dealing with something thick and physical to speculate about this. Now
it is also possible, like I said before, you know there's a
question about how much is this focused on the idea that there's
an act and the act has to be done a formal ritual
act with certain parameters. So is the act putting it on the
floor or is the act anyway putting it in and even if
it's in the wall? Or it could be here part of the
issue is is that the vessel doesn't act does a has an
effect of raising the sanctity. It's in a כלי שרת kli sharet
and that sanctifies it to the next level where now it can
be brought on the altar. And if that's true, then you could
ask the question about what is the nature of the way, and
this is discussed in other גמרות, Gemoras, of the way כלי שרת
kli sharet is מקדש mekadesh things that are in it. Is it
that it's מקדש mekadesh things that are in its airspace or is
it מקדש mekadesh things that are resting in it? So it could
be part of the question about the function and the way the
כלי שרת kli sharet works. But yes, those are you know those
are the implicit questions. So what do you want to say?
Is the issue as we've been saying, the normal way or not,
or is the issue what action can about what action can we
assume there was כוונה? kavana? And רש"י Rashi uses a language of
נתכוון. nitkaven. In other words if you do something, if it gets
into the vessel through a certain way—where where
does רש"י Rashi say נתכוון? nitkaven?
He says at the very bottom of the previous עמוד. amud.
He uses that language of—he says והכא שמאיליו נכנס בכלי והוא
לא נתכוון. Vehacha sheme'elav nichnas becheli vehu lo nitkaven.
Oh yes, that was because of a specific issue as we said
by this issue of חפינה chafina when it says based on the
word ולקח velakach and this wasn't included in ולקח. velakach. But that
was about the stuff between the fingers. By the fingers we were
talking about the normal act. Now that we're talking about the act
of taking or the placing, רש"י Rashi did not say נתכוון. nitkaven.
No but in other words what I'm thinking is like you go
like this and you go like this and you go like this.
Right. Maybe some of those
acts appear sort of just haphazard like that they're right.
All I'm saying is you don't see that in the גמרא. Gemara.
The גמרא Gemara seems specifically to say is this כי דקמצי אינשי
ki dekamzi inshi like people do it, you know? I so I
don't see that. I see the גמרא Gemara is trying to formally
define like look any type of a ritual the question is what
right exactly what constitutes doing that you know doing doing that formal
ritual. But here the question is it might be about the vessel.
If you look at תוספות Tosfos at the end of בעי רב
פפא, Ba'ei Rav Pappa, תוספות Tosfos quotes a גמרא, Gemara, you know
the line that starts like six lines before the end of that
תוספות, Tosfos, זבחים דף פ"ח. Zevachim Daf Pey-Chet. He says אמר שמואל
כלי שרת אין מקדשין אלא מבפנים. Amar Shmuel kli sharet ein mekadeshin
ela mibifnim. Okay and then the question
is what constitutes בפנים.
bifnim. So to think that this might be a question of the
כלי שרת, kli sharet, you know this you could ask the question
is it a question about the act of putting the קומץ kometz
in or is it the act or is it the nature of
how the כלי שרת kli sharet function? And anyway the גמרא Gemara
does not conclude. So if we had a תוכה בעינן ואיכא Tocho
ba'inan ve'ika כהן kohen that did this then what would you do?
Let's take... Okay, and then the question is what constitutes בפנים? Bifnim?
So to think that this might be a question of the כלי
שרת, Klei Shares, you know, this could ask the question: is it
a question about the act of putting the קומץ Kometz in, or
is it the nature of how the כלי שרת Klei Shares functions?
And anyway, the גמרא Gemara does not conclude.
So if you had a total amateur כהן Kohen that did this,
then what would you do?
You would have to—well, hopefully you could say just put it back
into the bottom again.
But you don't know, but then is that—why not? No, put it
into the bottom.
Well yeah, take it out, put it back in, so either way
you see—anyway, בעי מר בר רב אשי. Bayei Mar Bar Rav Ashi.
So now Mar Bar Rav Ashi asks, you know, carrying on this
approach of רב פפא Rav Pappa to ask these speculations, these types
of
questions: אפיכיה למנא, Afcheih Lemana, you turn the vessel upside, you know,
upside down, ודבקיה לקומץ בארעיסה, Vedavkia Lekometz Be'ar'isa, and you took the
קומץ Kometz and you stuck it on the floor of the vessel.
But you put it on the floor of the vessel when it
was no longer functioning as a container. For example, what I mean
is right here—Charlie, pass me the bowl there.
Thank you. What a perfect, what a perfect visual aid.
Do we have a קומץ? Kometz?
Right, I don't have a קומץ. Kometz. You went ahead and you
did it like this, but it's sticky, so you stuck it on
the floor. So you did stick it on the floor of the
vessel, and it is in the airspace of the vessel, but it's
not being contained, it's not being supported by—I mean stuck, sorry, but
it's not being, sort of, the gravity isn't holding it into the
vessel in the way vessels normally operate. Would that work or not?
מהו? Mahu? הנחה בתוכו בעינן והאיכא? Hanacha betocho beinan ve'ika?
Well, well, this isn't exactly לפני, Lifnei, this isn't that we said
is said by the act of the burning of the קטורת. Ketores.
This is just, you know, you haven't gotten to the altar yet.
Yes.
Someone else says: Does דבקיה לקומץ בארעיסה Devakia Lekometz Be'ar'isa translate to
the underside of the vessel? So like...
Oh, like this.
Either that or flip it over. Put it over and put it
on...
like that? Yeah.
But then
it wouldn't even be
תוך. Toch. Let me see. רש"י Rashi
says... No, there's no רש"י Rashi on this. Okay, maybe that could
be. I understood ארעיסה, Ar'isa, the... yeah, ארעיסה, Ar'isa, I don't know,
I guess ארעיסה Ar'isa is a different word than the word it
said before which
was, you know, שוליים Shulayim normally is the word for what it
says for the normal like inside base. Maybe... let's take a look
at the way the גמרא Gemara frames the
question. הנחה בתוכו בעינן והאיכא. Hanacha betocho beinan ve'ika. See, that's why
I think that the... that Seinfeld's idea is very difficult. Why is
it called בתוכו? Betocho? It's not בתוכו. Betocho.
He also goes on to say, excuse me, and the מאירי Meiri
explains the vessel's turned upside down with the flour placed on the
outside. With the what? Flour. Yeah. Flour. And he's only translating...
Yeah, yeah.
On the... on the... upside down flour on the outside of its
concave bottom.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. So תוספות Tosafos has that read. תוספות Tosafos has
that read.
As to whether the space is considered to be the equivalent of
the inside.
Right. Okay, so that was the read of תוספות, Tosafos, but I
wasn't reading it that way. תוספות Tosafos based on another גמרא Gemara
has the idea that you have the... you have it upside down
but it's... the base is curved and there's a hollow in this
part as well. So that could be... so that could be a
case of תוך. Toch. Okay, that could be. So it could be
that. תוספות Tosafos suggests that as a read but I also think
it's possible that you actually literally stuck it on the floor but
the floor
is
upside
down. It would be bringing that to the altar, I
mean, it
seems very disrespectful to be doing that.
I hear that.
Maybe you flip it over, but if it's an issue of an
act, not a vessel, right, that's a good question. If it's an
issue of how the vessel operates, not the act of placing, if
you corrected it afterwards without doing a replacement, would that work? Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara doesn't know. בעי רב פפא. Bayei Rav Pappa.
So those were questions about the קמיצה. Kemitza. You see רב פפא
Rav Pappa liked raising a lot of questions. Yeah, a lot of
questions by the קמיצה Kemitza and by the חפינה. Chafina. מלא חפניו
Melo Chofnav שאמרו. She'amru.
Now this is similar to the... a little bit to the question
about between the fingers. The fill of your hands when you do
the scooping by the קטורת. Ketores. מחוקות Mechookos או O גדושות? Gedushos?
Is it like we talked about the קומץ, Kometz, right, the קומץ
Kometz was מחוק Machook in the sense of you used your thumb
and your pinky to smooth it out and it was exactly smooth
and even. How about this, when you take the scooping, you know,
and you got... so what do you do with like the stuff
on the top here? Do you have it exactly like smoothed out
or is it like, you know, is it heaping? What's the story?
So I... yeah, I don't know exactly how you would do it,
you'd have to like use your arm or something.
No, but you need both of them.
How are you going to use your arm? Oh yeah, that's true.
I don't
know. Maybe if you would have used the fire pan on top
of it, it would have solved it, I don't know. אמר ליה
רב אשי לרב פפא Amar Leih Rav Ashi LeRav Pappa תא שמע.
Ta Shma. Come and here we have a ברייתא. Braisa. מלא חפניו
Melo Chofnav שאמרו She'amru לא Lo מחוקות, Mechookos, not smoothed out, cause
maybe that wouldn't even be possible as we're talking, ולא Velo גדושות.
Gedushos. shot and not heaping, because maybe that's not מלא חפניו. melo
chofnav. If it's heaping, it's not, it's more than the fill of
your hands, אלא טפופות, ella t'fufot, but like a little bit like
a floating, which basically means it's like it's a little curvature over
the top, okay? So it's not a heaping spoonful, but it's not
a complete smoothed down, it's got a little curve on the top.
Okay, תנן התם. Tnan hatam. Now we get to back to this
question about the act of קמיצה k'mitsa and and putting it and
the קומץ kometz into the vessel which is like a קבלת דם
kabalas dam in the vessel and also how that relates to the
חפינה. chafina. So let's take a look. תנן התם. Tnan hatam. נשפך
הדם על הרצפה ואספו פסול. Nishpach hadam al haritzpa v'asfo pasul.
If after the שחיטה shechita of an animal, the blood, for a
קרבן, korban, goes straight and hits the ground and then you scoop
it from the ground into the vessel, that's invalid. It has to
be caught from the animal directly into the vessel. מן הכלי על
הרצפה Min hakli al haritzpa if after it was caught in the
vessel it spilled on the ground, ואספו כשר, v'asfo kasher, then you
gather it it's כשר, kasher, which is quite fascinating. Once that part
was done right, it went from the animal to the vessel and
it was sanctified in the vessel, then you have to bring it
and throw it on the altar. If you trip and spill and
it goes on the ground and then you get it from the
ground and you put it back in the vessel, from the vessel
to the altar, you're fine. Okay, so actually that does not have
to be without interruption. That's okay. So מנא הני מילי. Mina hani
milei. First let's establish where we get that from and then that'll
serve as our paradigm for similar things regarding the מנחה mincha and
the חפינה. chafina. So where do we get that from? דתנו רבנן,
Detanu rabanan, we taught: ולקח מדם הפר, V'lakach midam hapar, the כהן
kohein shall take from the blood of the ox and he shall
put it on the altar. So מדם הפר, midam hapar, like the
ox, means מדם הנפש, midam hanefesh, like the blood that represents the
actual soul of the ox itself, the lifeblood. So that's after the
שחיטה, shechita, like the heavy squirting of the blood, that's considered to
be the
lifeblood, מדם הנפש. midam hanefesh. ולא מדם העור, V'lo midam ha'or,
not from the blood that comes from the skin, like I don't
know I guess it means the, what is that called, the blood
that runs like in the capillaries, like not coming out of the
veins or the arteries, but just, if you when you cut yourself,
like if you cut your skin and there's a little bleeding, is
there like a tiny, what's that, capillary? Probably capillary. Capillaries or something.
Like subcutaneous. Yeah, that type of, not that blood. Blood that's really
pouring
out. I understand, but it's not, it doesn't represent lifeblood.
Okay. ולא מדם התמצית, v'lo midam hatamtzit, so that's also, that's more
like the blood when it's not squirted, when it's just like the
remnant of the blood. So it has to be the lifeblood, that's
one thing you learn out. Now
מדם הפר, Midam hapar, now we're going to do is we're going
to play around a little and take the מ mem from מדם
הפר midam hapar and read it דם מהפר. Dam me'hapar. Blood has
to come straight from the ox into the vessel. דם מהפר יקבלנו,
Dam me'hapar yekabelenu, you have to catch it straight from the ox.
And therefore it can't first hit the floor and that was the
דרשה drasha we were going
for. אי סלקא דעתך מדם הפר, Ei salka datach midam hapar, מדם
אפילו מקצת דם. midam afilu miktzat dam. Let's say no, that's not
what you use the מ mem for, to move the מ mem
to the word הפר. hapar. מ mem means some, normally the מ
mem means from, but not all of it, and maybe it's coming
to tell you that you don't have to catch all of the
blood. No, you can't say that's the דרשה. drasha. ואמר רב יהודה,
V'amar Rav Yehuda, רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says, המקבל, hamkabel, when you're
catching the blood, צריך שיקבל כל דמו של פר, tzarich sheyekabel kol
damo shel par,
you have to catch all of the blood, שנאמר וכל דם הפר
ישפוך אל יסוד המזבח. shene'emar v'chol dam hapar yishpoch el yesod hamizbeach.
Well, you pour
all the blood. So now of course that's only לכתחילה. l'chatchila. Right.
So first of all it's only לכתחילה, l'chatchila, בדיעבד bedieved you don't,
but nevertheless it's saying we would not have learned the דרשה, drasha,
maybe דוקא dakka the דרשה drasha has to tell you that בדיעבד
bedieved it's okay if it's not all. But the גמרא Gemara is
rejecting that. No, since we know לכתחילה l'chatchila you need all, we're
not going to read the word מדם midam to say some. We're
going to use the מ mem to tell me דם מהפר, dam
me'hapar, it has to come straight from, of course,
straight from the ox.
Right, I was going to say, I've never been in a slaughterhouse,
but I imagine you would need a pretty large vessel if you're
trying to catch
all the blood you've collected.
But no, that's not how it's reading. But it is reading all
דם הנפש. dam hanefesh. So I don't know exactly where it identifies
the דם הנפש, dam hanefesh, but even so I imagine like what
do you need,
you need like like a like a garbage bag, like a big
ten gallon garbage pail or something to get the... I don't know.
So it's pretty shocking. אלא שמע מינה, Ella shema mina, but since
it doesn't mean from the blood, we hear it means מדם הפר,
midam hapar, דם מהפר יקבלנו, dam me'hapar yekabelenu, you move the
מ mem around.
דקסבר, D'kasavar, and here it spells out the mechanics of that דרשה:
drasha: גורין ומוסיפין ודורשין. Gurin umosifin v'dorshin. You can take away, add
on, and then do your דרשה. drasha. So you cut away the
מ, mem, you place you paste it back onto the word הפר,
hapar, and then you do your
דרשה drasha דם מהפר.
dam me'hapar. Okay.
Because it says דם הנפש dam hanefesh and below דם מהפר. dam
me-ha-par. Yeah, but so כל הדם kol ha-dam is כל הדם kol
ha-dam of the significant דם. dam. Once we've identified what is the
דם dam that matters, all of that דם dam you have to.
That was presumably what they were saying. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this. Now, בעא רב פפא, Ba'ei Rav Pappa, great. We've
got that as our model. Let's talk about how it applies to
חפינה. chafina. רש"י Rashi says we're not bothering to talk about how
it applies to קמיצה kmitza because we know already the הלכה halacha
by קמיצה kmitza that so but let's talk first about let's talk
how it applies to חפינה. chafina. So let's take a look. בעא
רב פפא, Ba'ei Rav Pappa, so he asks the following question.
Where am
I? נתפזר הקטורת ממלא חפניו מהו. Nitpazer ha-ktoret mi-melo chofnav mahu. You
do the חפינה chafina and now what are you supposed to do
with the חפינה? chafina? You put it into the כף, kaf, right?
So this is similar. It's like the שחיטה shechita into the vessel,
the קמיצה kmitza into the vessel. You're doing the חפינה, chafina, you're
going to put it in the כף. kaf. But now what happens?
You slip and some of that חפינה chafina hits the floor. Can
you take it from the floor to the כף? kaf? Is it
like the blood hit the floor without going straight into the vessel
and it's no good? Or is somehow this
different? Okay. Guys, no no no, we're not in the קודש קדשים.
Kodesh Kodashim. We're doing the... we're not doing the burning on the
coals. We're going... we're out here on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, right? You're
getting everything ready. You're scooping up from the big container and you're
putting your מלא חפניו melo chofnav into the ladle that you're going
to bring it. And as you're scooping it here and going to
put it in the ladle that you're going to bring it, some
of it spills. Is that like some of the blood spilled and
now you have to do the whole thing again or not?
Okay. That wasn't on the מזבח? mizbe'ach?
No, no, it was on the floor, on the
עזרה azarah at after the coals. He's on the floor and he's
doing this. Okay so what's the הלכה? halacha? נתפזר הקטורת ממלא חפניו
מהו. Nitpazer ha-ktoret mi-melo chofnav mahu. What's the story? ידו כצואר בהמה
דמי ופסולה. Yado k-tzavar behema dami u-psula. It's a great little image.
Your hand, which is holding onto the
קטורת, ktoret, and the קטורת ktoret is like the blood that's going
to be used ritually. So your hand is now like the throat
of the cow. And when you release it, it's like the releasing
of the blood and it has to go straight into the
vessel. Okay. דמי ופסולה. Dami u-psula. או דלמא ככלי שרת דמי ולא
פסולה. O dilma k-kli sharet dami v-lo psula. Or maybe no, because
often we say the body of the כהן kohen is like a
כלי שרת. kli sharet. And the כהן kohen is sanctified and we
sometimes objectify the body of the כהן kohen as a type of
a vessel, of a כלי שרת. kli sharet. So when he takes
it from the original box, the original container, it's already in the
כלי שרת. kli sharet. That was, as it were, the blood, the
ritual thing being put into the vessel. And not... it's not the
move to go from the hand into the ladle. That already is
that act and it's not a problem. Okay. ולא פסולה V-lo psula
and it's down as
תיקו. teiku. So it's an unanswered question. Now, the two issues here.
One is why are we not raising this question by the קמיצה,
kmitza, we're jumping straight to the חפינה? chafina? And this points to
a difference between the act of חפינה chafina and the act of
קמיצה. kmitza. First of all, I will remind you that we know
you have to do an act of קמיצה. kmitza. The גמרא Gemara
had a question whether you needed even to do an act of
חפינה, chafina, right? It said maybe just that amount. You maybe didn't
even have to do that act of חפינה chafina outside, right? To
scoop it originally. Now here all of this sort of assumes, all
the questions of רב פפא Rav Pappa assumes you have to do
an act of חפינה. chafina. And he's asking does it have to
be this way or that way. He is assuming you need the
act. But nevertheless, the act of חפינה chafina is of a different
nature than that of קמיצה. kmitza. And this is spelled out very
nicely by the תוספות ישנים. Tosafot Yeshanim. So anybody who has eyes
that are much better than mine, okay, but if you take a
look here at the תוספות ישנים Tosafot Yeshanim where he says the
first wide line in the middle, נתפזרו, Nitpazru, you see that all
like after the bottom of the תוספות Tosafot in the very tiny
bit. נתפזר הקטורת ממלא חפניו מהו. Nitpazer ha-ktoret mi-melo chofnav mahu. תימא
לרב רבי יוחנן מדשביק לקומץ. Teima l-rav rabi yochanan mi-deshavik l-kometz. It
didn't ask the question by the קמיצה. kmitza. ונקט קטורת v-nakat ktoret
and it's dealing with the קטורת. ktoret. משמע דבקומיץ פשיטא ליה. Mashma
de-v-komitz peshita leh.
It's obvious by the קמיצה kmitza that it has to go straight
into the vessel. ואי לאו יפינה מלא מלא הקומץ היינו הך. Ve-i
lav yafina melo melo ha-kometz hainu hach. And if it's the question
about are they the same. So again, it's one of these issues
of are you learning חפינה chafina from קמיצה kmitza or not. So
what makes this different than the קמיצה kmitza question? דאמר רבי, De-amar
Rabi, so פשיטא דגבי קומץ הוי כצואר בהמה. peshita de-gabei kometz havei
k-tzavar behema. It's obvious that the קמיצה kmitza is based on the
model of the blood and the throat of the animal. לפי שיש
ארבע עבודות במנחה. Lefi she-yesh arba avodot be-mincha. Like I was telling
you, there are four things you do in the מנחה. mincha. כנגד
ארבע עבודות של דם. Ke-neged arba avodot shel dam. כדאמרינן במנחות. Ki-damrinan
be-menachot. And one of the עבודות avodot is קמיצה kmitza is שחיטה.
shechita. And the going of the blood into the vessel is the
putting of the קומץ kometz into the vessel. So of course it
follows exactly and if it spills it's a problem, it's like the
blood spilled. אבל בקטורת מבעיא ליה. Aval be-ktoret mibaiya leh.
It's a question by the קטורת. ktoret. לפי שאין כלי לחפינה. Lefi
she-ein kli l-chafina. אלא משום דלא אפשר. Ela mishum de-lo efshar. Why
do you put it in the ladle? You remember why you put
it in the ladle? Only because you can't physically manipulate keeping it
in your hands and carrying in the firepan. But there's no act
of קבלה בכלי. kabala bi-kli. like there is an act of קבלה
kabalah of the דם dam in a vessel. דלא דמי לקמיצה delo
dami lekmitza היא במקום שחיטה hi bimkom shechita וקידוש הכלי vekidush hakli
במקום קבלת הדם. bimkom kabalas hadam.
So it’s not exactly analogous. תוספות Tosfos also makes the other point.
תוספות Tosfos says listen to the other difference. When you do the
קמיצה, kmitza, what's left over is of a different quality. It's what's
going to be eaten. When you do the שחיטה, shchita, the blood,
what's left over is a different quality. It's going to be eaten.
When you do the קטורת, Ktores, it's not like it'll בורר borer
on שבת, Shabbos, you know, טוב מרע. tov me’ra. This קומץ, komets,
the other leftover קטורת Ktores will be burnt on a different day.
It's not like this is going to be burnt and this somehow
is שיריים. shirayim. It's all equivalent. So the act of חפינה chafina
is not conceptually similar. Number one is pointed out by the תוספות
ישנים. Tosfos Yeshanim. The act of putting it in a vessel was
only needed practically because of how you convey it. There's not a
formal act of קבלה בכלי kabalah bichli like there's a קבלה kabalah
of the דם dam in a vessel and there's a קבלה kabalah
of the קומץ komets in a vessel. It's not that same ritual
act that's parallel. And therefore we could also say the act of
taking the חפינה chafina initially is not like an act of שחיטה.
shchita. It's not like an act of קמיצה. kmitza. It's not separating
the stuff on the מזבח mizbe'ach from the stuff not on the
מזבח. mizbe'ach. Fundamentally it's all the same, it's just taking the right
measure. So what this רב פפא Rav Pappa does is that brings
back nicely that discussion earlier of do you even need an act
of מלוא חפניו? melo chofnav? Maybe you don't even need the act,
maybe you just need the measure. So the questions of רב פפא
Rav Pappa assume you need the act, but the question is still
let's face it, even if you need to do the scooping, it's
not exactly the same as שחיטה shchita and קבלת הדם, kabalas hadam,
as קמיצה kmitza and putting it into the vessel. These are not
the same type of ritual acts that are עבודות avodos and that
each one is sort of doing something of significance. The first act
of חפינה chafina is not separating what can be on the מזבח
mizbe'ach and what can't be on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. And the second
act of putting it in the vessel is only a practical need
because of how you're going to convey it. So therefore we have
to ask the question, does it really matter therefore if you spill
from the חפינה chafina before putting it in the ladle or not,
because maybe that's not a whole ritual process like the שחיטה shchita
and like the קמיצה. kmitza.
I'm just curious if scooping some off the ground would even get
off the ground, right?
Excellent. We're going to get to that in one
second. So the חפינה chafina is
a חפינה chafina again, it's a review. The חפינה chafina is measuring
the amount
and
getting it into your hands,
scooping it into your hands and then putting it into a ladle.
Right. So then the קמיצה kmitza is getting it from the ladle?
No, the קמיצה kmitza is only by a מנחה, mincha, not by
the קטורת. Ktores.
Right, that's correct.
Okay, yeah we're contrasting different things.
Okay, yeah what happens as I take it out of this ladle?
No, no, here we're talking about spilling it out of the ladle.
No, no, we're spilling it from your hands as you're transferring to
the ladle and it scatters. That's exactly parallel physically to doing the
קמיצה kmitza from the מנחה mincha and transferring that to the vessel.
So you're doing that on the what, as a solid? We're assuming
it's a semi-solid.
Oh, like tiny little like powdery types of stuff.
I have a different question, but we've got it in here.
Wait, the קומץ komets now you're talking, not the חפינה. chafina. Right.
And we're putting it into the vessel and I'm opening up my
hand. Here I'm taking a floury type
item,
two hands, right, I'm not putting it in the vessel but I'm
holding it over the vessel and I'm putting it in.
Right, or I don't know exactly, maybe you go like that, right.
But if the vessel's big enough you're not going to scatter it.
But still, as soon as you open your hand because it's not
a solid mass, it's a dust almost, it's going to start flying
around.
Well I don't know if it's that thin, meaning the, again I
don't know exactly what the incense looks like, but I don't know
if it's so, I mean, דקה מן הדקה.
daka min hadaka.
Well that is true. Yeah, I don't know, I don't know what
its density is.
Going back to the קמיצה, kmitza, when I, we're worried about it,
but if I put my hand in, any way you want to
do it, I have קמיצה kmitza all over my hand. Right. I
got קמיצה kmitza all over my hand and we're only talking about
the קמיצה kmitza in the middle.
Right, well that's a good question. Meaning I don't know the answer
this is raised before about what do you do about the stuff
that sticks on your hand? If it's the קמיצה kmitza maybe it's
שיריים shirayim if it's not the stuff between the fingers. But if
it's the חפינה chafina how do you get the exact מלוא חפניו
melo chofnav if there's some stuff that sticks on? So again, I
don't know its exact physical constitution about whether it's sticky or not
or will adhere or not. Yeah, I don't know. I don't know
the answer to that.
It says dry hands but I've never seen it mentioned in ש"ס.
Shas.
Yeah, I don't know. Okay, so that's the question. Okay. And it's
a very and it's conceptually what I want you to appreciate and
again to make it clear what we're dealing here with is not
putting it on the fire. We're talking about the חפינה, chafina, we're
talking about from the hands into the ladle. If something spills is
that like the דם dam going into the vessel, the קמיצה kmitza
going into the vessel? It has to go directly or not. And
part of this question is even if you need an act of
חפינה chafina it clearly is of a different quality, both the act
of חפינה chafina better quality than the act of קמיצה, kemiza, the
act of שחיטה, shechita, and the act of putting it in the
ladle is a different quality than the act of putting the blood
going into the vessel and the קמיצה kemiza because again, these are
more needed out of practical necessity, not as much they are not
an עבודה. avoda. That at least seems to be the case, these
very good points of difference. I say that because רמב"ם Rambam by
the way, in quoting this גמרא, Gemara, let me find you the
רמב"ם, Rambam,
rules לחומרא, lechumra, and here's what the רמב"ם Rambam rules. Here's just,
I just want you to hear the language of the רמב"ם. Rambam.
The רמב"ם Rambam says like this, he says, חפינת הקטורת עבודה, chafinat
haktoret avoda, the
act of חפינה chafina is an עבודה, avoda, not like we've sort
of been suggesting. Not only is it needed, it's an עבודה, avoda,
והמחשבה פוסלת בו, vehamachshava poselet bo, if
you have wrong thought, which is what we're going to get to,
but everything we've been saying now is just not the way. And
then the רמב"ם Rambam says, if he says, נתפזר קטורת מידו על
הארץ ואספה, nitpazer ktoret miyado al ha'aretz va'asafa, כל אלו ספק ולא
יקטיר ואם
הקטיר הורצה. kol elu safek velo yaktir ve'im hiktir hurtza. Okay, so
the רמב"ם Rambam says that it's a ספק safek about this, but
again for us it seems there's a very good reason to say
no because of all of these points of difference. How much is
it like those other things or not? The other thing I did
want to just say again symbolically before continuing is the idea that
יד כהן כצואר בהמה, yad kohen ketzavar behema, thinking about this like
the blood squirting out and the קטורת ktoret coming out just again
ties into that theme of that קטורת ktoret is מכפר mechaper like
a קרבן. korban. Again, we normally tend to think of the קטורת
ktoret as something of a completely different type of an עבודה, avoda,
but the emphasis here paralleling it to the מנחה mincha and the
שחיטה shechita makes us again connect it very much to that sense
of the כפרה kapara of קרבנות, korbanot, which is a theme that
the גמרא's Gemara been introducing. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues.
בעא רב פפא, ba'ei Rav Papa, so רב פפא Rav Papa asks,
חישב בחפינת קטורת, chishev bechafinat ktoret,
Michael's question and what we already heard the spoiler in the רמב"ם.
Rambam. Okay, if you had a thought when you were doing the
חפינה chafina to do it on the wrong day, okay, would that
be like a פיגול pigul thought, which only can take place during
the עבודות? avodot? מהו, mahu, what's the הלכה? halacha? מי אמרינן יליף
מלא מלא ממנחה, mi amrinan yalif melo melo mimincha, again
the question about מלא melo from מנחה. mincha. מנחה mincha we know
the קמיצה kemiza is like שחיטה shechita and a פיגול pigul thought
will be effective by and you know create problems by מנחה. mincha.
מה התם מהניא בה מחשבה הכא נמי מהניא בה מחשבה, ma hatam
mahanya ba machshava hacha nami mahanya ba machshava, do we say the
same way there a מחשבה machshava helps, means is effective, makes invalidates
it, here too? או לא, o lo, or not? And the obvious
argument to say no is for what I said, this isn't an
עבודה. avoda. We've just got through saying there's reasons you need to
do it but that doesn't make it an עבודה. avoda.
So you know that's a whole, you know, sort of make that
a little bit more
generic anyway, because yeah even if you plan to be מקריב, makriv,
you know, מקריב makriv the קרבן korban and זורק zorek the דם
dam at a wrong time, okay. אמר ליה רב אשי בר אשי
לרב פפא, amar lei Rav Ashi bar Ashi leRav Papa, רב אשי
בר אשי Rav Ashi bar Ashi came to give him an answer.
תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear. הוסיף רבי עקיבא, hosif Rabbi
Akiva, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva added to the list of things that
you'll see that if you touch part of it you invalidate all
of it, הסולת, hasolet, the flour from a מנחה mincha or it
might be הקומץ, hakometz, but same idea. והקטורת, vehaktoret, the incense, presumably
both that you bring on a daily basis and on יום כיפור.
Yom Kippur. והלבונה, vehalvona, that's the also the incense that you would
have with the לחם הפנים, lechem hapanim, והגחלים vehagechalim and the coals,
what is the what way are they similar? שנגע טבול יום במקצתן
פסל את כולן. shenaga tevul yom bemiktzatan pasal et kullan. If a
טבול יום, tevul yom, somebody who went to the מקוה mikva that
day and has the status of a שני, sheni, touches part of
them he invalidates all of them. Meaning in this vessel, this כלי
שרת, kli sharet, you've got a lot of coals, or you've got
a lot of סולת, solet, a flour of a מנחה, mincha, or
a lot of קטורת. ktoret. And I with my finger touch one
little piece of it. So separately these are physically separate objects, maybe
only the piece I touched should be טמא tamei and the rest
should be טהור. tahor. But the הלכה halacha is that a כלי
שרת kli sharet unifies everything that's in it, if it sanctifies what's
in it it unifies what's in it and it's all considered one
unit and I invalidated it all. Okay, what wonderful, what does it
have to do with me? So let's take a look what the
גמרא Gemara says. Yes?
Only on יום כיפור? Yom Kippur?
Yes. So how could he have an intent to do it on
another time?
No, he scoops it on יום כיפור Yom Kippur and he's planning
that he's going to bring it on the eleventh of תשרי. Tishrei.
I mean it's a crazy thought. The same way anytime a כהן
kohen has a פיגול pigul thought it's a crazy thought. He should
be just, if he had that thought, would it invalidate? All right,
he's a צדוקי, Tzadoki, he's a להכעיס, lehachis, I don't know. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this, קסלקא דעתך, kasalka datach, now we're
assuming, מדפסל טבול יום, midepasal tevul yom, since a טבול יום tevul
yom invalidates, פסלה נמי לינה, pasla nami lina,
so לינה lina invalidates. Now the connection is that the reason a
טבול יום tevul yom can invalidate all of it is because of
the assumption of how the כלי שרת kli sharet operated, as I
told you. Which means that the כלי שרת kli sharet elevated the
קדושה kedusha of these things. If I just put my sandwich in
a כלי שרת, kli sharet, it doesn't get elevated. Only things that
are, you know, of that status and they're, you know, to be
elevated are elevated. So their status is they're being The concept is
קדושת הגוף, Kedushat HaGuf, intrinsically sanctified. And if that's how come it
operates to unify it, it also means that if it stays overnight,
if it becomes invalid, because anything that's sanctified in a כלי שרת
Klei Sharet of קדושת הגוף, Kedushat HaGuf, an intrinsic validity, becomes invalid
after night. ומי
דלינה פסלה, Umi d'lina pasla, if night invalidates, so פסלה נמי מחשבה,
pasla nami machshava, so time matters. And if time matters, your incorrect
thought also invalidates. Now this is a crazy comparison, but first of
all I have to tell you just something about, even before you
get to the comparison, it's not that crazy, but anyway, before you
get to the comparison is the language of קסלקא דעתך. kasalka daitach.
Okay, קסלקא דעתך kasalka daitach normally means to say we thought to
say this, but then we realized we were wrong and that actually
this wasn't a good argument. But here the גמרא Gemara doesn't reject
it. It just says here's our assumption. Okay, here's why we're making
this comparison and it doesn't challenge it. So that's a
fascinating—והתניא Veha'tanya is another example. Normally והתניא Veha'tanya means as a challenge:
how can you say this, we have the ברייתא. Braita. But sometimes
והתניא Veha'tanya means a support. But here קסלקא דעתך kasalka daitach like
almost never means that we're keeping with it. Here it's just to
say here's our assumption and we're not going to challenge it. That's
point number one. But point number two is look, I get the
argument that if a כלי שרת Klei Sharet creates a קדושת הגוף
Kedushat HaGuf then it becomes invalid overnight. But that's not my question.
My question isn't: is nighttime relevant? My question is: is the act
of חפינה Chafina an עבודה avoda so that your thought is relevant
at that time? I don't want to know if nighttime is relevant.
If this has the קדושה Kedusha to be invalid, wonderful. It has
the קדושה, Kedusha, it could become invalid. But only when you're doing
an עבודה. avoda. Since the whole point we raised before is: is
חפינה Chafina an עבודה avoda or not? And that seems to be
completely taken for granted. That's why by the way, since the רמב"ם
Rambam rules that thought does invalidate, the רמב"ם Rambam starts by saying
חפינה עבודה היא. Chafina avoda hi. Therefore thought invalidates. Okay, but prove
to me the חפינה Chafina is an עבודה. avoda. That is the
basic point missing from the argument. Okay, by the way because of
a little bit because of that question, also because there was a
better place to bring this from rather than a ברייתא Braita of
רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, there's a more explicit משנה, Mishna, we get
a major save as you turn the page, because if you turn
the page you see בעי רב פפא. Ba'ei Rav Pappa. Now look
how little we have left to do. This huge תוספות Tosafot is
basically trying to figure out: why did the גמרא Gemara make the
proof it did before about לינה lina and פסול יום psul yom
and פסול יום psul yom from a ברייתא Braita if you had
a better משנה Mishna to bring the argument from? And this leads
to this whole long discussion about that and that's basically—that, I know,
but this is huge. Anyway, this allows us to finish the דף
daf today. So, on to the next question. בעי רב פפא, Ba'ei
Rav Pappa, רב פפא Rav Pappa asked: So that was one question
about the חפינה. Chafina. Now here's another
question: חישב בחתיית גחלים מהו? Chishav b'chatiyat gechalim mahu? How about the
scooping of the coals? Is the scooping of the coals an עבודה?
avoda? Let's say you scoop the coals and you had a thought.
Now what was your thought? רש"י Rashi has two versions of what
your wrong thought could be on the—on the coals of the קטורת.
Ketoret. You tell me two versions of what the wrong thought of
the
coals—as you're doing the coals you're planning on doing the קטורת Ketoret
at a different time? So not only it has to mean that
the scooping's an עבודה, avoda, but it's an עבודה avoda that's part
of the עבודה avoda of the קטורת. Ketoret. Or what's the other?
You're scooping the coals and you're assuming you'll use the coals at
a wrong time, not you'll use the קטורת Ketoret at a wrong
time, you'll use these coals at a different time. מהו, mahu, what's
the story? מכשירי מצוה כמצוה דמי? Machshirei mitzvah k'mitzvah dami?
Since it's preparatory to the burning of the קטורת, Ketoret, it's like
the burning of the קטורת, Ketoret, and presumably if the חפינה Chafina
of the קטורת Ketoret is an עבודה, avoda, this becomes then similar
and part of that process and also becomes an עבודה? avoda? או
לא, O lo, or not? תיקו, Teiku, we don't know. So here
you get again just to see the trajectory.
Yesterday we raised the possibility you didn't even need a חפינה Chafina
at all, it's enough to have מלא חפניו. melo chofnav. Today we're
assuming you need a חפינה Chafina and the question is about all
of the specifics: if you scoop it this way, if you scoop
it that way, right? All the specifics and also does it have
to go straight from the חפינה Chafina into the ladle? How much
is it exactly like the עבודות? avodot? And now to the point
that really a מחשבת פיגול machshevet pigul is relevant and really making
it ממש mamash like one of the עבודות. avodot. That's quite a
trajectory of how much it's needed, like it might not be needed
at all to really making it a serious—a serious עבודה, avoda, serious
part of the ritual.
It's a huge
thing: מכשירי מצוה כמצוה דמי. machshirei mitzvah k'mitzvah dami.
Yeah, I mean that's obviously you can apply that a little generically.
I mean there's questions—we can't, we can't just say oh, since you
know—they're not, you can't throw everything into the same—assume it has the
same answer. But there are—there are questions about it, for example do
you make a ברכה bracha like the גמרא Gemara says when you're
בעל לעשות, ba'al la'asot, you know, סוכה sukka you make a ברכה,
bracha, when you make—when you—when you make your—your, you know, your שופר
shofar or whatever, you know, when do you make a ברכה bracha
on, on, you know, on מכשירי מצוה? machshirei mitzvah? Does the מצוה
mitzvah of, does the idea of הידור מצוה hiddur mitzvah apply to
מכשירי מצוה machshirei mitzvah or only to the מצוה mitzvah itself? There's
like a lot of areas where the question of that applies. Not
all the same answer.
Okay? מה ש- mah she- you have to say לשם leshem what?
Well, that's a כוונה kavana issue; that's actually a כוונה kavana issue.
So, okay, so גמרא Gemara says like
this: בעי מיניה מרב ששת, bei minei me-Rav Sheshet, they asked from
רב ששת. Rav Sheshet. What? הולכה בשמאל מה? holacha b'smol mah? Finally,
because this was the question we had in the משנה. Mishnah. Now
that we finished talking about the חפינה chafina and how much we
have ritualized that act that turns it into an עבודה avodah or
not, now we're going to talk about the conveying of everything into
the קודש קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim, right? How much is that something that
can be done with the left hand? How much is that an
עבודה? avodah?
Now, that's going to be the answer, right? First of all, what
was even your question? The answer's obvious. But the question starts with,
according to the way רש"י Rashi understands, not יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
but on a normal day, when you take the blood to the
altar, or you take the קומץ kometz to the altar, the normal
הולכה holacha that you do in the מקדש, Mikdash, can that be
בשמאל? b'smol? Because the issue of הולכה holacha is fascinating. On the
one hand, it's one of the four, it's one of the four
עבודות, avodot, and for example, if you have a פסול pasul כהן
kohen do it or you have a פיגול pigul thought during it,
it's a problem. On the other hand, the גמרא Gemara calls it
an עבודה שאפשר לבטלה, avodah she-efshar l'vatla, that in theory you can
get away without doing the הולכה holacha if you שחט shecht right
by the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So how much is the הולכה, holacha, which
is really just getting it from place A to place B, considered
a full עבודה avodah or not? And the question is, can't, so
in many ways it is an עבודה, avodah, but can it be
done with the left hand? So let's take a look. הולכה בשמאל
מה? holacha b'smol mah? אמר ליה רב ששת, Amar lei Rav Sheshet,
רב ששת Rav Sheshet says, תניתוה, tanituha, we taught it in our
משנה: Mishnah: נטל את המחתה בימינו ואת הכף בשמאלו, natol et hamachtah
biymino v'et hakaf b'smolo, you're bringing the incense with your left hand.
So again, assuming that the הולכה holacha of the קטורת ktoret is
similar to the הולכה holacha of קרבנות, korbanot, notice again now the
full way we're lining it up: חפינה chafina equals שחיטה, shechita, putting
it in the כף kaf equals catching the blood in the vessel,
so the bringing of the קטורת ktoret into the קודש קדשים Kodesh
Kodashim equals bringing of the blood to the מזבח. mizbe'ach. We are
ממש mamash making everything equivalent to a classic עבודה. avodah. So if
that can be done with the left hand, presumably we can say
a normal הולכה holacha can be done with the left hand. So
גמרא Gemara says: ונפשוט ליה מהתם, v'nipshot lei mei-hatam, so why didn't
you learn it out from another הולכה holacha of the left? הרגל
שהימין בשמאלו לבית העורה לחוץ, haregel she-hayamin b'smolo l'veit ha-ora l'chutz, that
when the כהן kohen carries these different limbs of the עולה olah
to the altar, remember we had that whole thing about the lottery
and carrying the limbs? So it says that he carries
the right hind leg in his left hand, okay, so and you
know the place to, so in that type of a case he's
carrying one of the limbs of it to the altar in his
left hand. Okay, so don't you see you can do it with
your left hand, a conveyance? So גמרא Gemara says: no, אם מהתם
הוי אמינא, im mei-hatam hava amina, הני מילי הולכה דלא מעכבא כפרה,
hani mili holacha d'la me'akva kapara, that's a type of a conveyance
which is not necessary for the atonement. It's not of the blood.
You get the atonement of the קרבן korban without burning the limbs.
אבל הולכה דמעכבא כפרה, aval holacha d'me'akva kapara, something is necessary like
the blood or like the קומץ kometz or like the חפינה chafina
which is going to be burnt on the inside, which is part
of what is the necessary process כפרה, kapara, I would say לא,
lo, maybe it cannot be done with your left hand. קא משמע
לן kamashma lan that it can. Okay, and we're going to continue
tomorrow to argue whether it can be done with your left hand.
But again, notice how shocking this is, right? It went from saying
these things might not even be so necessary. Now, of course, the
הולכה holacha is in the פסוק. pasuk. The פסוק pasuk does say
והביא. v'hevi. There was never a question whether you needed to do
the חפינה. chafina. There wasn't a question whether you needed to do
the conveyance. But nevertheless, we are ממש mamash lining everything up with
the עבודות, avodot, not just to say if it's required by an
עבודה, avodah, it's required here, or if it's bad by an עבודה
avodah like פיגול, pigul, it's bad here. We're lining it up to
say that if it's good here, you can argue in the reverse
that it's good by a classic עבודה. avodah. And I want, by
the way, also point out as I did when we read the
משנה, Mishnah, that here you know the left hand has to be
good because you're using two handbreaths. So the left hand is part
of the process here. You could have just said even if it
is an עבודה, avodah, it's a natural exception here because anyway you're
using your left hand. But the גמרא's Gemara assuming it's so much
lined up with the עבודות avodot that if it's good here we
can argue in reverse that it's good by the עבודות. avodot. So
we will see more of this argument tomorrow.